Guide to the Alvin and Heidi TofflerPapers,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Alvin and Heidi TofflerPapers,
1955-1984
Toffler, Alvin.
ca. 117,000 items (263 boxes and l oversize folder).
Columbia University Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Butler Library, New York, NY 10027.
4078547
Biographical Note
Alvin (1928- ) and Heidi Toffler, authors and futurists.
Scope and Content
Correspondence, telephone logs, lecture/administrative files, manuscripts, research files, personal papers, reviews, press clippings, tearsheets, and memorabilia relating to the many projects Toffler and his wife worked on from 1950 to 1985. The collection is divided into closed and open series. Closed files include all correspondence; telephone logs; administrative files pertaining to lectures, contracts, and business memos; and personal papers. Open files consist of clippings, notes, manuscripts, publishers' "dead matter," tearsheets of articles and books, press clippings, interviews, and galleys. The correspondence includes letters from a great variety of people, such as Betty Friedan, Jonas Salk, Newt Gingrich, Ed Koch, and many other politicians and celebrities. There are research files for virtually every project that Toffler was involved with, including his books "Future Shock" and "The Third Wave." The press clippings files are extensive and range from research topics to reviews, and cover countries from Australia to Switzerland. Lecture files also from Toffler's television/video production compnay, Triwave Productions, Inc., which include scripts, contracts, and materials relating to all stages of production. The many manuscripts, proofs, and galleys are in various stages of revision and include Toffler's extensive corrections and notes.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into 9 series:
Series I: Correspondence
Series II: Appointment Calendars
Series III: Phone Messages
Series IV: Office Files
Series V: Administrative Files
Series VI: Office Files
Series VII: Book Files
Series VIII: Tri-wave Productions
Series IX: Clippings and Magazines
Subjects
Koch, Ed.; Friedan, Betty.; Gingrich, Newt.; Salk, Jonas, 1914-1995.; Social history--1945-; Social change.; Civilization, Modern--1950-; Correspondence; Authors, American--20th century.
Access Restrictions
Restricted materials are closed except by written permission until the death of the last surviving of Alvin Toffler, Heidi Toffler, and their daughter Karen Toffler.
This collection is located off-site. You will need to request this material from the Rare Book and Manuscript Library at least twenty-four (24) hours in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.
Acquisition
06/17/87 M-87-06-17 Toffler, Alvin and Heidi Gift
Gift of Alvin and Heidi Toffler, 1987.
- Series I: Correspondence
  Boxes 1-83 are RESTRICTED. See description sheet for conditions.
  - Subseries I.1: Chronological
    - [n.d.]; 1950-52; 1954-55; Jan. 1956 - April 1958 (Box 1)
    - May 1958 - Dec. 1959 (Box 2)
    - 1960-62 (Box 3)
    - 1963-64 (Box 4)
    - Jan. 1965 - June 1966 (Box 5)
    - July 1966 - Dec. 1968 (Box 6)
    - Jan. 1969 - July 1970 (Box 7)
    - Aug. - Nov. 1970 (Box 8)
    - Dec. 1970 - April 1971 (Box 9)
    - May - Dec. 1971 (Box 10)
    - 1972 (Box 11)
    - 1973 (Box 12)
    - 1974 (Box 13)
    - [n.d] (1970-74?); Jan. - Aug. 1975 (Box 14)
    - Sept. 1975 - Dec. 1976 (Box 15)
    - Jan. 1977 - July 1978 (Box 16)
    - Aug. 1978 - May 1979 (Box 17)
    - June 1979 - April 1980 (Box 18)
    - May 1980 - April 1982 (Box 19)
    - May 1982 - March 1983 (Box 20)
    - April - Aug. 1983 (Box 21)
    - Sept. 1983 - Feb. 1984 (Box 22)
    - March 1984 - Jan. 1985 (Box 23)
  - Subseries I.2: Alphabetical
    - . A (1980-81) - C (1982) (Box 24)
    - Chaplain, Richard (1980) - G (1980-81) (Box 25)
    - G (1982) - M (1980-81) (Box 26)
    - M (1982) - P (1981) (Box 27)
    - P (1982) - Strudler, Hal (1980) (Box 28)
    - T (1980-81) - XYZ (1982) (Box 29)
  - Subseries I.3: Foreign
    - Alphabetical by country, 1980-1982 (Box 30)
  - Subseries I.4: Vox Pop
    - Nonsubstantiative, 1969-1978 (Box 31)
    - Substantiative, 1970-1979 (Folder 31)
- Series II: Appointment Calendars
  - Appointment Calendars, 1963; 1965 (Box 33)
- Series III: Phone Messages
  - Phone Messages, 1970-1973 (Box 34)
  - Phone Messages, 1974-1977 (Box 35)
  - Phone Messages, 1978-1980 (Box 36)
  - Phone Messages, 1981-1982 (Box 37)
  - Phone Messages, 1983-1985 (Box 38)
  - Messages from projects, 1972-1984 (Box 38)
- Series IV: Office Files
  - Subseries IV.1: General
    - Additives (food) - Powell, Adam Clayton (Box 39)
    - Presidential Politics - Zworykin, V. K. (Box 40)
  - Subseries IV.2: Projects
    - Advocates for the Arts - Antioch (Box 41)
    - APPROTEC - Center for Adaptive Learning (CAL): Prentice Hall research (Box 42)
    - Center for Adaptive Learning (CAL): Tenth grade correspondence - Committee for Anticipatory Democracy (CAD): Membership (Box 43)
    - Committee for Anticipatory Democracy (CAD): National Participation Act - EcoThinktank (Box 44)
    - Edwin Schlossberg, Inc. - Futuremics (Box 45)
    - Future Option Room - Nihon Marketing Center, Inc. (Box 46)
    - Omnibus Video - Salzburg Seminars 1966-67 (Box 47)
    - Salzburg Seminars 1968-72 - Women of the Year 2000 (Box 48)
- Series V: Administrative Files
  Some include correspondence
  - Subseries V.1: General
    - The Adaptive Corporation - The EcoSpasm Report: Spain (Box 49)
    - The Ecospasm Report: US - Invitations/Requests, 1971 (Box 50)
    - Invitations/Requests, 1971-75 (Box 51)
    - Invitations/Requests 1976 - Learning for Tomorrow (Box 52)
  - Subseries V.2: Lecture Files
    Lecture files are chronological. General files (such as Lecture expenses) begin each annual sequence
    - Lecture Requests 1971 - May 1971 European Trip (Box 54)
    - June 1971 Japan Trip - 31 May 1972 (U. of Ontario) (Box 55)
    - 4 June 1972 (U. of Cincinnati) - 20 Feb. 1973 (Denver) (Box 56)
    - 21 Feb. 1973 (Toronto) - Lecture expenses 1974 (Box 57)
    - Lecture requests 1974 - Lecture requests 1975 (Box 58)
    - 11 Jan. 1975 (Washington D. C.) - 5 June 1975 (Washington D. C.) (Box 59)
    - 9 June 1975 (Monterey, Mexico) - 15 Dec. 1975 (US Senate) (Box 60)
    - Lecture expenses 1976 - 25 June 1976 (Washington D. C.) (Box 61)
    - 24 Aug. 1976 (Louisville) - 29 March 1977 (Miami) (Box 62)
    - 1 April 1977 (Fort Myers) - 14 April 1978 (Indianapolis) (Box 63)
    - 26 April 1978 (U. of Northern Illinois) - 2 April 1979 (Miami) (Box 64)
    - 3 April 1979 (Hilton Head) - 4 Dec. 1979 (Brazil) (Box 65)
    - Lecture requests 1980 - 18 Oct. 1980 (Boston) (Box 66)
    - 22 Oct. 1980 (French Lick) - 3 Feb. 1981 (Munich) (Box 67)
    - 10 Feb. 1981 (Las Vegas) - 27 April 1981 (Acapulco) (Box 68)
    - 1 Sept. 1981 (Japan) - Lecture requests 1982: foreign (Box 69)
    - 20 Jan. 1982 (Tokyo) - 21 July 1982 (Venezuela) (Box 70)
    - 11 Aug. 1982 (Honolulu) - 21 Oct. 1982 (Washington D. C.) (Box 71)
    - 9 Nov. 1982 (Copenhagen) - 13 April 1983 (Boca Raton) (Box 72)
    - 18 April 1983 (Palm Springs) - 12 Sept. 1983 (Boston) (Box 73)
    - 16 Sept. 1983 (Orlando) - 15 Dec. 1983 (France) (Box 74)
  - Subseries V.3: General (cont.)
    - 75. List of names - Permissions: Future Shock (granted 1972) (Box 75)
    - Permissions: Future Shock (granted 1973) - General 1982 II. (Box 76)
    - Permissions: general 1982 III. - Southend Press (Box 77)
    - Technical requests - Testimonials for Future Shock (Box 78)
    - Third Wave: Bantam (Art) - Offshoot possibilities (Box 79)
    - Third Wave: Press List - Serial (First) I. (Box 80)
    - Third Wave: Serial (First) II. - William Morrow (Advertising) (Box 81)
    - Third Wave: William Morrow (Art) - Triwave Productions: Bank reconciliation (Box 82)
    - Troad Inc. (Wing Project) - Writing by others: Requests (Box 83)
- Series VI: Office Files
  Boxes 84-263 are UNRESTRICTED
  - Subseries VI.1: General
    - Administered prices - Anticipatory Democracy (A/D): Alternatives for Washington II. (Box 84)
    - Anticipatory Democracy (AID) - Alternatives for Washington III. - Hawaii (Box 85)
    - Art and automation - Arts in Detroit I. (Box 86)
    - Arts in Detroit II. - Block, Max (Box 87)
    - Buck, Sgt. Carl. H. - CBS/EVR (Box 88)
    - Child labor: Migrant - Child labor: Used (Box 89)
    - Childs, Lydia Marie - Convention (Box 90)
    - Countries: Algeria - Culture Consumers: Bureaucracy (Box 91)
    - Culture Consumers: Canada - Culture hucksters (Box 92)
    - DiSalle, Michael - Education book: Third wave (Box 93)
    - Education: Brain - Futuristics II. (Box 94)
    - Education: Futuristics III - Scope (Box 95)
    - Education: Second wave - Technology (Box 96)
    - Education: Tenure - Work (Box 97)
    - Eisenhower - Federal Trade Commission (Box 98)
    - Filibuster - Harris, Roy I. (Box 99)
    - Harris, Roy II. - Hoffa, James (Box 100)
    - Housing - IBM automation I. (Box 101)
    - IBM automation II - X (Box 102)
    - Information retrieval - Labor in fiction (Box 103)
    - Labor Racketeering - Leisure (Playboy Panel) II. (Box 104)
    - Leisure (Playboy Panel) III. - Libraries: EFL Project notes (Box 105)
    - Libraries EFL Project: used - McClellan, Sen. John L. (Box 106)
    - McGee, Sen. Gale - Magazines I. (Box 107)
    - Magazines II. - Menshikov, M. A. (Box 108)
    - Merrick, David - Metropolitan Museum (Box 109)
    - Military Justice - Morse, Sen. Wayne (Box 110)
    - Moses, Robert - Natural gas (Box 111)
    - Negro history - Orthodontics: not used (Box 112)
    - Orthodontics: used - Pentagon air power (Box 113)
    - People: Auls, Lawrence - Prigogino, I. (I.) (Box 114)
    - People: Prigogino, I. (Box 115)
    - People: Taylor, Gordon R. - Private bills (Box 116)
    - Quadruplets - Right Wing ultras and bigots (Box 117)
    - Schlesinger, Arthur - Social Indicators I. (Box 118)
    - Social Indicators II. - Stress III. (Box 119)
    - Stress IV - Teacher: Day in the life of (Box 120)
    - Teacher Tenure - Toys (Box 121)
    - Water Pollution I-V (Box 122)
    - Water Pollution VI. - Winston-Salem I. (Box 123)
    - Winston-Salem II - Women (H) (Box 124)
    - Women: Lady Legislators - Work: Leisure II. (Box 125)
    - Work: Leisure III. - Xerox I. (Box 126)
    - Xerox II - Zanuck, D.(Not used I.) (Box 127)
    - Zanuck, D.(Not used II.) - Zworykin, V.K. (Box 128)
  - Subseries VI.2: Projects
    - ABC/Space Shuttle - Anticipatory Democracy (A/D): New York (Box 129)
    - Anticipatory Democracy (A/D): New York RPA - Suggested programs and learning (Box 130)
    - Anticipatory Democracy: (A/D): Surveys - Center for Adaptive Learning -- (CAL): Asbell (Box 131)
    - Center for Adaptive Learning (CAL): Communications magazine - Eleventh grade text (Box 132)
    - Center for Adaptive Learning (CAL): Maston - Prentice Hall working papers (Box 133)
    - Center for Adaptive Learning (CAL): Proposed projects - Warshofsky (Box 134)
    - Committee on Anticipatory Democracy (CAD) - Financial Services for Education (Box 135)
    - Gingrich/Toffler on Social Security - National Humanistic Education (Box 136)
    - National Volunteer Awards - Society of Magazine Writers (SMW) (Box 137)
    - Russell Sage Foundation proposals - Salzburg Seminar (Box 138)
    - Silberman, Richard T. - State Dept. (Dixon) (Box 139)
    - Technology - Women in the Year 2000 (Box 140)
- Series VII: Book Files
  These include Bound volumes, Proofs, Galleys, Manuscripts, Drafts, Files, Clippings, Notes, and Miscellaneous materials.
  - Subseries VII.1: The Adaptive Corporation 1985
    - Copies of Social Dynamics and the Bell System, (Corrected proofs) (Box 141)
    - Corrected proofs (Box 142)
    - Superseded drafts, General research files (Box 143)
    - Research files on AT&T: Articles - Consumer (Box 144)
    - Research files on AT&T: Coporate Goals - Modular Corporation (Box 145)
    - Research files on AT&T: Organization - Regulation (Box 146)
    - Research files on AT&T: Social Consequences - Western Electric (Box 147)
    - Interview files (Box 148)
    - Reel-to-Reel interview tapes (Box 149)
  - Subseries VII.2: The Culture Consumers 1964
    - Bound copies with corrections; Proofs; Galleys (Box 150)
    - Manuscripts, Superseded drafts, Front matter, Layout materials (Box 151)
    - Superseded drafts (Box 152)
    - General research files: Business - Culture Consumers (Box 153)
    - General research files: Government - Theatre (Box 154)
    - Chapter files: Chs. 1-6 (Box 155)
    - Chapter files: Chs. 7-10 (Box 156)
    - Chapter files: Chs. 11-13; Miscellaneous files; Comments about the book (Box 157)
    - Clippings: Reviews 1964-66 (Box 158)
    - Clippings: Reviews 1971;1973; Random House PR 1973; Notebooks (Box 159)
  - Subseries VII.3: The EcoSpasm Report 1975
    - Page proofs; Master galleys; Original manuscript (Box 160)
    - Drafts; Research files; Clippings (Box 161)
  - Subseries VII.4: Future Shock 1970
    - Paperback copy with corrections; Dust jacket; Proofs (Box 162)
    - Proofs (Box 163)
    - Galleys (Box 164)
    - Galleys (Box 165)
    - Drafts (Box 166-171)
    - General research files (Box 172)
    - Chapter files: Chs. 1-8 (Box 173)
    - Chapter files: Chs. 9-15 (Box 174)
    - Chapter files: Chs. 16-20 (Box 175)
    - Files on syndication and excerpts (Box 176)
    - Advertising materials (Box 177)
    - General clippings re: Future Shock and Toffler (Box 178)
    - General clippings re: Future Shock and Toffler (Box 179)
    - Clippings: Best Seller lists - Business II. (Box 180)
    - Clippings: Business III. - Foreign press (Box 181)
    - Clippings: General reviews - Medicine and psychology (Box 182)
    - Clippings: Planning - Youth (Box 183)
    - Clippings: Re: Business: Advertising - Transportation (Box 184)
    - Clippings: Re: Impact: Arts - General I. (Box 184)
    - Clippings: Re: Impact: General II. - Science and technology (Box 185)
    - Clippings: Foreign: Australian - Colombian (Box 186)
    - Clippings: Foreign: Communist Countries - French II. (Box 187)
    - Foreign clippings: French III. - Irish (Box 188)
    - Foreign clippings: Italian - Spanish (Box 189)
    - Foreign clippings: Swedish - Swiss (Box 190)
    - Index (Box 191)
    - Future Shock: Musical: Scripts; Clippings; Related materials (Box 192)
    - French translation (Le Choc du Futur): Manuscripts (Box 192)
    - French translation (Le Choc du Futur): Drafts; Notes; Index (Box 193)
    - German translation: Drafts; Notes; Related materials (Box 194)
  - Subseries VII.5: The Futurists 1972
    Edited by Toffler
    - Proofs; Galleys; Drafts (Box 195)
    - Drafts (Box 196)
    - Biographies of contributors; Clippings; Notes; Photocopied materials (Box 197)
  - Subseries VII.6: Learning for Tomorrow 1974
    - Galleys (Box 198)
    - Galleys (Box 199)
    - Manuscripts (Box 200)
    - Original manuscript (Box 201)
    - Interview files (Box 202)
    - Research files: The Phillips Program; Outlines (Box 203)
    - Files on contributors: Bart, P. - Buchen, I. (Box 203)
    - Files on contributors: Eurich, N. - Rojas/Eldridge I. (Box 204)
    - Files on contributors: Rojas/Eldridge II. - Toffler, A. (Box 205)
    - Files on contributors: Villegas, J. - Wren-Lewis, J. (Box 206)
    - Index; Notes; Updates for book; Clippings (Box 206)
  - Subseries VII.7: The Money Managers
    - Galleys; Manuscripts; Drafts (Box 207)
    - Drafts; Chapter files: Chs. 1-6 (Box 208)
    - Chapter files: Chs. 7-12 (Box 209)
    - Chapter files: Chs. 13-15 (Box 210)
    - Research files on Mutual Funds: Bibliographies - Effect on Market (Box 210)
    - Research files on Mutual Funds: Future of - Scope and growth (Box 211)
    - Interview files (Box 211)
  - Subseries VII.8: Previews and Premises 1982
    - Proofs (Box 212)
    - Proofs (Box 213)
    - Manuscripts (Box 214)
    - Manuscripts; Drafts; Outlines (Box 215)
    - General research files; Interview files (Box 216)
    - Interview files (Box 217)
    - Interview files (Box 218)
  - Subseries VII.9: The Schoolhouse in the City 1968
    - Proofs; Galleys (Box 219)
    - Manuscripts; Drafts (Box 220)
    - Drafts; Files on contributors: Brain, G. - Graves, G. (Box 221)
    - Files on contributors; Havighurst, R. - Wilcox, P.; Clippings; Notes (Box 222)
  - Subseries VII.10: Social Dynamics and the Bell System 1972
    - Manuscripts (Part I only); Microform of finished text; General research files (Box 223)
    - Research files: Chs. 1-11, Part I (Box 223)
    - Research files: Parts 2-4; Files on new goals (Box 224)
    - Research files: 1985 Bell Organization; Interview files; Notes. (Box 225)
  - Subseries VII.11: The Third Wave 1980
    - Galleys (Box 226)
    - Miscllaneous. galley pages; Manuscripts (Box 227)
    - Manuscripts (Box 228-235)
    - Drafts (Box 236)
    - Drafts (Box 237)
    - Chapter files: Checking copy, Editorial suggestions, Not used, Notes, Superseded drafts, Used. (Box 238-257)
    - Introduction; Ch. 1 (Box 238)
    - Ch. 2 (Box 238)
    - Chs. 2A-4 (Box 240)
    - Chs. 5-7 (Box 241)
    - Chs. 8-9 (Box 242)
    - Chs. 10-12 (Not used IV.) (Box 243)
    - Chs. 12 (Not used V. - used) (Box 244)
    - Ch. 13 (Box 245)
    - Chs. 14-15 (Not used I.) (Box 246)
    - Chs. 15(Not used II.) - 16 (Box 247)
    - Ch. 17 (Box 248)
    - Ch. 18 (Box 249)
    - Chs. 19-20 (Box 250)
    - Ch. 21 (Checking copy - Not used II (Box 251)
    - Ch. 21 (Not used III. - used) (Box 252)
    - Ch. 22 (Checking copy - Superseded drafts) (Box 253)
    - Ch. 22 (Used); Chs. 22-23 (mixed) (Box 254)
    - Ch. 23 (Checking copy - Superseded drafts I.) (Box 255)
    - Ch. 23 (Superseded drafts II. - Used); Chs. 24-25 (Box 256)
    - Chs. 26-28; General files (Box 257)
    - One Oversize folder: Proofs (Box 366)
- Series VIII: Tri-wave Productions
  - Transcripts; US Scripts (Box 258)
  - US Scripts; Japanese Scripts (Box 259)
  - Japanese Scripts; Printed Materials; Files (Box 260)
- Series IX: Clippings and Magazines
  - Articles by Toffler, [n.d] 1955-57 (Box 261)
  - Articles by Toffler: 1956-78; Articles mentioning Toffler (Box 262)
  - Magazines and pamphlets with articles by Toffler, 1968-84 (Box 263)